Hi everyone.
皆様はじめまして。
If you saw the last record, welcome back. I'm Yue.
前回の記録を見てくれた皆様はお久しぶりです。ユエです。
Maki from prefectural road 25.
はい！こちら県道25号のマキです！
What?
えっ？
What happened? Where is the camera?
どっきり？カメラはどこだ？
What do you mean?
えっ、なんで？
There is a camera in front of you.
カメラ、前についているけど。。。
Yeah right...
あっ、そうだった。。。
Where did you even learn to speak like this?
と言うか、どこでテレビ口調覚えた？
Anything wrong?
どうかした？
Nothing. It's just that you don't hear it much nowdays.
いや、単純に今時あまり聞かないからさー。。。
I have a lot of text books and some DVDs.
本とかDVDをいっぱい持ってる。
That's great. I didn't know such compilation existed.
へー、すごいね。今時こんなに参考資料があるのだな。。。
Yeah,
だね。
It was pretty hard a few years back but now it's a lot easier.
数年前までは難しかったけと、今は楽。
It'd be great if there was the same for English.
へー、英語で同様のものがあればいいのに。。。
By the way, how do you lookup for stuff?
ちなみにどうやって探しているの？
Hm?
ん？
I just lookup for the latest manga and anime.
最新の漫画やアニメで探している。
Mangas!?!?
漫画か～い！
Wait. Is there even untranslated manga other there?
え？そもそも向こうに翻訳なしの漫画ってあるの？
There is a few but they are pretty expensive and rare.
専門店なら見かける、でも数も少ないし高い。
I see...
へ～。。。
You could do the same with comics...
アメコミでやってみたら？
Comics are actually a good idea...
コミックスはいいアイデア。
Welcome to Itsuki, the lullaby village.
ようこそ子守唄の里五木。
Lullaby village?
子守唄の里？
Maybe a silent village?
静かな里ってことかな？
Silence with a motorcycle...
静かな場所でバイクを。。。
I'm kind of sorry...
なんかすみません。。。
Oh, more cherries
おー、ここにも桜が！
Most petals already felt...
ほとんど散っちゃってるけどね。。。
Well, we are a week late after all.
1週間遅いからな。。。
I always heard hanami is short but didn't expect it was only 1 week with 1 or 2 weeks extra like this...
花見は短いとは聞いていたけど、まさか1週間が満開で、今のような風景が1〜2週間続くとは。。。
Yeah, the rain makes them fall faster as well.
まーね、雨とかで早く散ったりするし。。。
Woah, that's a huge river
大きい川だな！
Where's this?
どこここ？
This is not a river. This is a dam lake. I think it was called Ichifusa dam lake.
ここは川じゃなくてダム湖だよ。たしか名前は市房ダム湖だったはず。
It's a great spot for sight seeing.
景色見るには最高の道だね。
First time but it's a nice place.
初めて来たけどいいよねここ。
No cars, great view.
車なし、綺麗な景色。
Once again on a narrow road?
また狭い道？
What do you mean again? As if I'm always running on narrow empty roads...
またとは、人がいつもどこにあるか分からない狭い道を通ってるように。。。
Well, cars coming from the front are scary, but many times it comes with a good view, feels like you unlocking new paths.
いや、まあ〜対向車が怖いが、眺めがいいとこもおおいし、ひましないし、道を切り開いている感じがあるじゃん。
Well, I mean.
いや、ま〜。。。
I like this kind of road.
こう言う道も好きだけど。
But you seem to be ultra focused on the road so I thought it made you stressed out.
でもユエがあまりにも道路に集中しているからストレスかなって。。。
What? Really? I do have a lot of fun tho.
えっ？そう見える？いやいや、十分に楽しんでるよ。
You sure? Don't push yourself too much ok?
本当？無理しないでね。
Yeah, yeah.
はいは〜い。
But how about you? Not tiered?
そういえばマキさんわ？疲れていない？
Nah, I'm good. Thanks.
大丈夫、気にしてありがとう。
You sure? We do not take many breaks...
そう？毎回ほぼノンストップで走ってるけどな。。。
Now it's not that hot.
今はそんなに暑くないね。
You make small stop here and there, so it's all good thanks.
よく小休憩してるから大丈夫、ありがとう。
Don't push yourself.
無理はしないでよ。
Okey dokey
ホイホイ〜。
Hmm?
んー？
Ahh, I want to go straight ahead!
あ〜、まっすぐ行きたかったな〜。
What? You don't have the skills to go on this kind of road yet...
え？こんな道行く技術もないのに？
Yah... It might also be a private property...
いや、私有地の可能性があるから行かないけど。
True...
そうね。。。
Make sure to check beforehand.
事前に確認してよ〜。
Okay.
は～い。
I want to go to a forest track one day...
いつか林道行きたいな。。。
Those kind of road won't run away so take your time.
道は逃げないからゆっくり。
True. Let's go slowly at our pace.
確かにね、ゆっくりマイペースでいくか～。
It's soon the end, want to go somewhere?
そろそろここも終わるし、次どこ行く？
Well, I don't really know the area...
ここの近くはあまり知らないけど。。。
But I heard the road from Hitoyoshi to Ebino is pretty.
人吉からえびのの道が綺麗って聞いた。
Oh, that one. Sure thing.
あーあそこね。行ってみるか。
Thanks
ありがとう！
The Hitoyoshi loop!
人吉ループだ〜！
That's a huge leap!
結構飛んだな。
Couldn't you have a larger view?
もっと全体を見れる場所なかったの？
Nope, sorry.
いや〜、なかった。。。
Round and around.
グールグール～。
I'm starting to feel sick...
何か酔ってきた。。。
What?
えっ？
Wait!
んー。。。
Hmmm...
ん～。。。
How is it now?
これでどう？
It's a bit better thanks.
ちょっとマシ、ありがとう。
Glad to hear that.
よかった。
Maybe sit a bit on the left, make your body upright and have a flat sight?
ちょっと左に座って、体を真っすぐにして、目を水平にしてみたら？
Okay... I'll try.
わかった。試してみる。。。
We are about half now.
ここで半分くらいかな。。。
Looks like there is an escape, want to stop?
マキさん、止めれそうだけど、一休みする？
I'm ok for now, thanks to the picture in center.
真ん中の酔い止めでだいぶ楽になった、ありがとう。
Okay. Going on then.
オッケー、通過するよ。
Oh on the bridge now?
おー、もう橋の上？
About 3 fifths?
5分の3ぐらいかな～。
There is a nice view here.
いい景色だね！
You're not wrong.
ソウデスネ。。。
Ah right, the camera can only point forward.
あ〜、そっか、GoProは前しか見えないのか。
Looks like we are coming to a strait?
もうすぐ真っすぐになる？
You're not wrong.
ソウデスネ。。。
Can finally look around a bit more
やっと周りを見れる。
Are you okay?
大丈夫？
I'm totally don't feel sick...
ゼンゼンヨッテナイヨ～。。。
Really?
本当？
I am, I am.
ホントホント～。。。
Just wondering how I'm going to shoot sideways.
ただただ横撮影をどうしようかなって。。。
You can use a 360 camera, or put your GoPro on you helmet.
360度カメラやGoProをヘルメットにつけたら？
Hmmm, I'll think about it.
んー、考えておく。。。
Soon out of the tunnel.
トンネルをぬけるぞ！
I'm excited to see the other side!
向こう側を見るのが楽しみ。
Ohhh.
おー！
Oh?
お？
Hmm.
んー。。。
Look on the right!
右見て！
The right side looks great.
右すごいね！
It's such a good view!
凄い綺麗！
By the way, didn't we cross borders once again?
また県境超えた？
You saw that?
よく気付いたね。
In the tunnel there was a sign saying we entered Miyazaki prefecture.
そうだよ、トンネルの中で熊本県から宮崎県に入った。
Don't you have a visual?
映像はないの？
It was pretty shaky in the tunnel, but I found a nice snapshot.
トンネルの中は画面揺れがひどかったけど、この写真をを見ればわかるかな？
Ah, I can read the sign.
あ〜、読める！
Is this the edge of Ebino city?
あの下はえびの市の端っこかな？
This looks so peaceful.
のどかだね。
It sure is great to look down the view from a high place.
やっぱり高いところからの眺めは最高だね！
The southmost railroad crossing of Kumamoto!
熊本県最南端の踏切！
Actually you are back in Miyazaki.
まっ、ここって宮崎なんだけどね。
Wait? It is not?
えっ？そうなの？
Making a small stop.
止まるよ。
There is a lot of grass on tracks, do trains even go here?
線路が草で見えないけど、ここって電車通るの？
Not used since the 2020 flooding...
2020年の大雨から通らないね。。。
That's sad to hear... Hope it'll get back in business one day.
それは悲しい。いつか電車で行けるといいね。
We are almost there.
もうすぐで着くな。
I feel like I've seen this place before...
ここ見た事がある気が。。。
Is that so?
そう？
Can you say where we are?
ここってどこなの？
Here is Yatake station.
ここは矢岳町だよ。
I've never heard of this place...
ここは聞いたことがない。。。
I think it's the southmost point of Kumamoto, but many come here for a different reason.
熊本の最南端に位置すると思うけど、今行く場所を見に観光者が来てたくらいかな。。。
Ohhh!
おー！
Is that a locomotive?
これって機関車？！
SL Hitoyoshi, D51-170.
SL人吉、D51-170だね。
It has been resting here since the 70' if I'm not mistaken.
確か1970年代からここに休んでいるはず。。。
Mind if I take a closer look?
もっと近く見に行っていい？
Nono, take your time.
いやいや、ゆっくり見ていってね。
Yay!
ヤッター！
It's a real one.
本物だ〜。
Can we go in?
中入れるのかな？
It's huge!
大きいね！
There is a staircase and no forbidden mark...
階段ある、禁止なし。
Yay, analogue meters!
アナログメーター！
Is this where you throw coal in ?
ここに石炭を入れるのか。。。
I'm back.
戻ったよ〜。
Welcome back.
お帰り～。
Hope you didn't wait too long.
待たせてごめんね。
It's all good.
大丈夫だよ～。
Shall we go?
行こうか？
Not taking a look at the station?
駅のほうは見ないの？
I'll have a look then!
ちょっと見てくる！
Don't fall!
転ばないでよ～。
Okay dad!
大丈夫大丈夫！
That station was a blast!
この駅凄く良かったね〜。
Yeah, it's very quiet but I hope that locomotive will stay there a bit longer.
そうだね。結構静かだけども、まだまだ長くあそこにあのSLはいてほしいかな。。。
Yah, it's such a great opportunity to see that piece of history...
そうね、歴史的な乗り物を見れるチャンスだね。
But sadly the paint is really coming into pieces.
でもペンキが剥がれてきたな。。。
Well... It's free to visit so cannot really complain, can we?
ま～。。。無料でおいてくれているから仕方ない気もするけどね。。。
Yah...
そうね。。。
You're turning here?
ここで曲がるの？
Turning here.
曲がるよ～。
I've seen a sign for station but going to another closed station?
駅の漢字が見えたけどまた廃駅に行くの？
Secret!
ひーみーつー！
I see a building. Is that the station?
建物が見えるけど、あれが駅？
No, the station is a bit further.
いや、駅舎はその裏にあるよ。。。
Wait...
ちょっと待って。
Is this?
ここって？
I'm sure I've seen this place before...
ここ見た事ある気がする。。。
You see it from time to time in videos from people going around Japan.
日本一周勢の動画にちょこちょこ出るかね～。
God this is bugging me!
あ〜気になる！何だっけ！
I want to remember before finding the answer!
答えが見える前に思い出したい。。。
Good luck.
がんばれ～！
And...
はい！
Five!
五ー。
Four.
四。
Three.
三。
Two!
二～。
One!
一～。
Time's up!
時間切れ！
Ah!
あっ！
Got it!
分かった！
Here we are at the business cards station, also known as Okoba Station.
はいきました、名刺の駅、通称大畑駅。
Isn’t that the other way around?
普通は逆なのでは？
Well, it is more famous the business cards.
ま～、名刺を置く場所に固定せれているからな。。。
It's a shame because there is a switch-back over there but most come for the cards.
でもこの駅はスイッチバックもあるけど、ほとんど名刺のために来るのよね。。。
Looking at the inside from here, I can only see talismans.
ここから中見ると札にしか見えない。。。
Nah... It doesn't look like talismans... or does it?
いや～。。。おふだには見え。。。るか？
The owners of those business card will get angry at you!
この名詞の持ち主が怒るよ〜！
Hey! You were the one saying that!
いやマキさんが言ってたでしょ！
There is so many business cards here.
名刺がすごく多いね。。。
There is even some on the second floor.
2階にもチラホラあるね。。。
True! I wonder how they were able to stick them this high...
本当だ～、すごい、どうやって置いたんだろう。。。
Hope everyone did get a promotion...
みんな出世してるといいね。。。
You didn't leave your card, did you?
名刺を貼って行ってないような？
Hmm? I don't want to take space and want to do it myself...
ん～、場所取りたくないし、自分で頑張りたいかな。。。
Come to think of it, how were exams?
そう言えば、テストどうだった？
Don't ask...
聞かないで。。。
Ah, I see...
あっ、はい（察し）。。。
Somehow managed to get in the top 10%...
何とか30位以内にはなったが。。。
Wha? That's great!
えっ、すげ〜じゃん！
Exchange student I see...
さすが留学生。
You're smart...
頭いいんだね。。。
Nah, I just study a lot.
いや、勉強してるだけ。
I was always struggling to get a passing mark.
こっちは毎回赤点回避に必死だったのだが。。。
Ah, that's why you use a motorcycle and not a car!
あ〜、だから車ではなく、バイクなのか〜。
Yes?
そうだよ？
Apologize! Apologize to all motorcycle riders!
あやまれ！全世界のバイク乗りにあやまれ！
Well I might be in top 10% for kokugo, but I'm worst 1% to understand Kumamoto's dialect.
国語で何とか30位以内になっても、熊本弁の理解は300位なんだよね。。。
Smart-ass...
これだから勉強できる人は。。。
But it is true there is not many references to learn those...
でも確かに覚えようとするとなかなか資料がないよね。。。
Yeah, there are not many books or ways to learn dialects.
方言を覚えるための本とかないからね。。。
Nowdays there is videos on YouTube but they are very specific.
最近はYouTubeとかで見かけるが、特殊なシチュエーションとか、普段使いが少ない言葉とか。
I also found some websites for words.
単語をまとめていたサイトも見つけた。
Words huh?
単語ね。。。
Dialects are fun to learn but hard to come by...
方言は覚えるのが楽しいけど、なかなか見つからない。
Come to think of it you don't have a strong dialect...
そういえばユエって方言あまり使わないよね。
I see... Wait... You think so?
あー。。。あ？そう？
You don't say things like daken.
だけんとか言わないし。
Daken...
だけんね。。。
Well, it doesn't come out naturally.
なぜか方言が出てこないんだよね。。。
You had interest in dialect?
というかマキさんって方言に興味あるの？
A little bit.
ちょっとだけ。。。
I love how each dialect is unique in Japan.
日本の方言の違いが好き。
Wait. This view is great!
ちょっと待って、ここすごい綺麗！
The sunset is pretty. It would have been better with some cherries.
夕日がきれいだよね。。。もっと桜があったら最高だったんだろうな～。。。
It's on the road leading the Okoba station.
大畑駅に行くもうひとつの道だね。
It must be hard if you are in a car.
車だと大変そうだね。。。
Good thing you're on a motorcycle.
バイクで良かったね。
Well, this kind of curve where you cannot see the other end is pretty scary.
いやーまーこう言うびみょうに向こうが見えないコーナーが怖いんだよね。。。
Yeah. You have to put your feets out and make it strait on halt when you're on a motorcycle ...
そうね、止まる時は真っ直ぐにして、足を出さないとだね。。。
Cannot hear you!
あ～耳が～！
There there, it's okay now
まあまあ、大丈夫だよ。
Thank you.
ありがとう。
Time to go back to Kumamoto.
さて熊本に帰るか。
This gates seens different.
料金所の形全然違うね。
Here is an automated toll booth. You need a special etc card.
ここはETC専用ゲートだからね。ETCがないととおれない。
First time I use one...
こう言うタイプは初めてなんだよね。。。
Yay!
やったぜ～。
This has a funny structure...
なんか変な形。。。
Bars on the right are shut.
右のバーは下のままだね。
I think you go through here if you don't have the card...
そうね。ETCが使えない場合はそこを通るんだろうな。。。
Done with the 5th record...
さて、5話目も終わりか。。。
I feel like it took you a bit less time...
作成時間ちょっと短くなった？
A little bit...
ちょっとね。。。
Well still a beginner but you seem to have found your way young man.
まだまだ初心者だけど、自分の道を見つけたようだね青年。
Nah, still have a lot to learn...
いやいや、まだまだだよ。。。
Thank you for all the view and comments for the last record.
前回の記録のご視聴、コメント、広告ありがとうございます。
Sorry for missing out the greeting at the start.
記録を見直したのですが、冒頭のあいさつがなくてすみません。
Sorry, I was too excited about hanami...
ごめん、花見が楽しみだったから。
Greetings are important, but having fun is more important.
まー、挨拶は大事だけど、楽しむのも大事！
Okay...
だね。。。
There is some interesting comments from last record.
前回も面白いコメントがあったよ。
I wonder what people commented on.
前回は。。。何にコメントしているんだろう。。。
How did people find my birthday?!
なんで私の誕生日知っている人いるの？！
I didn't tell anyone!
誰にも言ってないよ！本当だよ。
Really?...
本当？
I wouldn't tell anyone.
誰にも言わないよ。
But I don't get the first one?
１番目はなに？
Hum? Ah, this is a well-used phrase and can be translated to "Yay! Maki is cute!".
えっ？。。。あー、これはよく使われるフレーズで、単に「マキさんが可愛い、やったぜ」を短くしたものだと思う。
Is that so?
そう？
The last one makes me really happy! Thank you!
最後のコメントすごくうれしい！ありがとう！
I'm really glad people don't find me annoying for not speaking japanese.
英語でしゃべってて見辛いと思うけど、それでも見てくれてありがとう！
Maki can speak Japanese but keeps speaking English to help me learn.
マキさんはちょっと日本語しゃべれるけど、英語の練習に付き合ってありがとうね。
It's no biggy. I try to sound more Japanese and I feel a bit less homesick thanks to you.
いやいや、ちょっとだけ合わせてるけど。。。英語使うことがないからおかげでホームシックと感じない。
I really recommend that place.
あそこはすごくお勧めですよ。
But since the road is narrow, beware of on comming cars. You can go early to avoid them.
ただ狭い道ですので、対向車に注意です。そのため早い時間帯で行くのがおすすめです。
Yeah, we went twice but the second time it was very crowded.
そうね、二回行ったけど、二回目は混んでたね。。。
It gets crowded arround 10am.
大体１０時以降は混みだす感じですかね。
That place was also a good place.
ここもよかったよね～。
Yeah, it was a very pretty good surprise.
ね、すごい偶然だった。
The road is new and straight so very easy to drive on.
道路が新しく、真っすぐで、すごく走りやすかったです。
And very easy to look around.
周りも見やすかった。
Well next is everyone's favorite, long distance trip!
さて、次回からみんな大好きゴールデンウイークのお話だ～！
Golden week didn't happen.
ゴールデンウィークなんてなかった。
Ah... Wait, you came with me didn't you?
あっ。。。いやいやマキさんも来てたじゃないか。
You mean the exile?
島流しのこと？
Yah, nah, I said exile a lot but we had fun right?
いや、ま～、こっちもよく島流し、島流しって言ってたけどたのしかったでしょ？
Heh heh
へへ〜。
It was a lot of fun actually.
結構楽しかったね。
I know right?
でしょ？
For this reason we'll stop commenting on the previous video. We will reply once the trip is done.
そのためこのコメ返しはいったんお休みさせてください。旅から帰ってから返事をしようと思います。
Sorry for breaking the format, but I hope you won't mind too much.
フォーマットが変わって、すみませんが、よろしくお願いします。
Well see you on the next record until then take care.
それでは皆様、また次の記録まで、ご安全に！
See you!
またね！